A Finding Aid to the Adolf Dehn Papers, 1912-1987, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Adolf Dehn papers
1912-1987
Archives of American Art
Dehn, Adolf, 1895-1968
AAA.dehnadop
Archival Resource Key
6.6 Linear feet
The papers of printmaker and painter Adolf Dehn measure 6.6 linear feet and date from 1912-1987. The collection contains extensive correspondence, as well as writings, exhibition announcements, catalogs, clippings, invoices, receipts, legal documents, scrapbooks, artwork, and photographs. There is also scattered correspondence of Virginia Dehn, mostly concerning her husband Adolf Dehn.
Provenance
The Adolf Dehn papers were donated in several installments from 1966 to 1985 by Adolf Dehn and his wife Virginia. Dehn's sisters, Viola Dehn Tiala and Olivia Dehn Mitchell, separately donated additional materials in 1971 and 1972. Olivia Dehn Mitchell also loaned the Archives letters from Adolf in 1983 for microfilming. Finally in 1989, Lillian Morrison, a friend and editor, donated a published book of Mura Dehn's poetry and a four page draft of a letter signed by Adolf Dehn.
Separated Material
The Archives of American Art also holds microfilm of material lent for microfilming. Reel 287 contains printed materials, including exhibition announcements, catalogs, magazines, and newspaper and magazine clippings. After filming, these materials were transferred to the Smithsonian American Art Museum/National Portrait Gallery Library. Reels 2938-2939 include 750 letters from Adolf Dehn to various family members. This material was returned to the lender and is not described in the collection container inventory.
Restrictions on Access
Use of originals requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Adolf Dehn (1895-1968) was well-known for his drawings, lithographs and watercolors which satirically chronicled the social and political milieu of his times, as well as poetic landscapes, many of which depicted the rolling hills and farmlands of his native Midwest. Although he worked mostly in New York, Dehn also spent substantial time traveling and working in Europe, the Middle East, South America, and the American mid-west.
Dehn was born on a farm in Waterville, Minnesota on November 22, 1895, he began his formal art education in 1914 at the Minneapolis School of Art (currently known as the Minneapolis College of Art and Design). As a student, his drawings were featured in the school's humor journal, The Minne-Ha-Ha and by 1917 he had published his first drawing in one of his favorite political journals, The Masses. Later that year he and fellow Minneapolis School of Art student Wanda Gág were among a select group of art students nationwide who won scholarships to the Art Students League of New York. After only eight months in New York, however, Dehn was drafted into the Army to serve in the final months of World War I, but he proclaimed himself as a conscientious objector and was sent to Camp Wadsworth in South Carolina for several months.
Dehn returned to New York, where his friend and mentor Boardman Robinson introduced him to lithography through the master printer George Miller and brought him to the Weyhe Gallery to meet Carl Zigrosser, an avid supporter of American printmakers. However, he soon left New York for Europe in September 1921 where he spent most of the following eight years. There he traveled with his sketchbooks to the cafes and opera houses of Berlin, Paris, and Vienna, as well as on hiking trips in the Alps. He became friends with the poet E.E. Cummings, Scofield Thayer, editor of The Dial, who published many of his drawings, and met the German artist, George Grosz, whose work he so admired. In addition to The Dial, his satirical drawings of jazz-age entertainments and European cafe life also appeared in, The Liberator, Jugend, Vanity Fair, and Simplicissimus. Finally during his stint in Europe, Dehn met and married the Russian dancer Mura Tsiperovitch. They were married in Vienna in 1926, but divorced sometime in the early 1930s.
Unfortunately Dehn's return to the United States coincided with the Great Depression of 1929 and sales of his work were slim. However in the 1930s, The New Yorker and Vogue began to publish his work. He continued to work in lithography and returned to Paris to work at the Atelier Desjobert, the print studio with whom he worked most closely throughout his life. In the late 1930s, Dehn began working in watercolors, mostly rural landscapes, and had a one man show of works in his new medium at Weyhe Gallery in 1938. In 1939 Dehn traveled through the Southwest and Mexico on his first Guggenheim Fellowship (he was awarded his second in 1951).
By the 1940s Dehn was an active member of both the American Artists Group and Associated American Artists; both organizations sought to popularize contemporary American Art, primarily through reproductions of fine art prints and commercial use of artists' designs on greeting card, calendars, and even wall paper. Appreciation for his lithographs and watercolors grew, and along with it his recognition. He also taught art classes a few summers; in the late 1930s at Stephens College, Columbia, Missouri where his friend Albert Janner-Christ was head of the art department and in the early 1940s at the Colorado Springs Fine Arts Center, where friend and mentor Boardman Robinson was the director. In 1955 he published Watercolor, Gouache, and Casein Painting, a manual on technique. Throughout the rest of his life he continued to travel, not only returning to Europe, but also visiting Afganistan, Cuba, Haiti, and a trip to Venuzuala on assignment from Standard Oil to document the oil industry there. On many of his later trips, he was accompanied by his wife, fellow artist, Virginia Engleman Dehn, whom he had married in November 1947.
Near the end of his long career, Dehn was elected in 1961 to the National Academy of Design as a full academician. He was later elected to the National Academy of Arts and Letters. After his death in 1968, his wife Virginia worked with the University of Missouri Press on the catalog Adolf Dehn Drawings (Columbia: University of Missouri, 1971).
Scope and Content Note
The papers of printmaker and painter Adolf Dehn measure 6.6 linear feet and date from 1912-1987. The collection contains extensive correspondence, as well as writings, exhibition announcements, catalogs, clippings, invoices, receipts, legal documents, scrapbooks, artwork, and photographs. There is also scattered correspondence of Virginia Dehn, mostly concerning her husband Adolf Dehn.
Found within the biographical materials are several address books, official travel documents, exhibition price lists, and a biographical sketch.
Correspondence, both personal and business, makes up the bulk of this collection. Dehn maintained long friendships with many fellow artists and his correspondence includes letters from Aaron Bohrod, Federico Castellon, Albert Christ-Janer, Wanda Gág, Gustav Goetsch, George Grosz, Reginald Marsh, Elizabeth Olds, Abraham Rattner, Boardman Robinson, Frederick Shane, William Smith, and Benton Spruance. Additional notable correspondents include print dealer and curator Carl Zigrosser; journalists Max Eastman, Joseph Freeman, Frederick Kuh; editor Scofield Thayer, and his former wife, the Russian dancer Mura Dehn (neé Tsiperovitch). Business correspondence includes letters from art schools, associations, museums, and galleries affiliated with Dehn, including the Weyhe Gallery; Associated American Artists, a gallery that promoted American art to the middle classes; and the Kennedy Gallery, which represented the Dehn estate upon the artist's death. There is also correspondence from companies and organizations that commissioned commercial work from Dehn, such as greeting card publisher, American Artists Group. Finally the correspondence of Virginia Dehn includes letters to and from the University of Missouri Press related to the publication of Adolf Dehn Drawings and condolence cards and letters from friends and associates after the Adolf Dehn's death in May 1968.
Writings include manuscripts for Adolf Dehn's manual on painting technique, Watercolor, Gouache, and Casein Painting (Studio Publications, 1955), as well as his entries on technique and watercolor painting for Encyclopedia Britannica. Writings by others includes the catalog Adolf Dehn Drawings, prepared by his wife Virginia Dehn, and published in 1971 by the University of Missouri Press. There is also a journal with handwritten poems attributed to Eileen Hall Lake.
Printed materials consists of exhibition announcements and catalogs from galleries featuring Dehn's work including the Weyhe Gallery and Associated American Artists; art school brochures and newsletters from programs which Dehn attended or taught; and newspaper and magazine clippings including examples of his editorial cartoons, which appeared in The Liberator, The New Yorker, and Vanity Fair, among other publications as well as clippings of news items related to the artist. This series also includes examples of Dehn's commercial work, such as book covers, calendars, and Christmas cards. Additional similar printed materials can be found in the scrapbooks. Artwork consists of only a few sketches attributed to Dehn, others to Eileen Lake Hall, and an etching by S.W. Hayter.
Dehn is well documented through numerous photographs, both alone and with others, including a portrait by the renowned photographer André Kertész. Additional vintage photographs include Dehn with family members, friends, and a series of photographs taken with his wife, Virginia Dehn at Atelier Desjobert, where he had been making lithographs since the 1920s.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 8 series:
Missing Title
Series 1: Biographical Material, circa 1920-1968 (Box 1; 10 folders)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1919-1982 (Boxes 1-4; 3.75 linear feet)
Series 3: Writings, circa 1920-1971 (Boxes 4-5; 0.25 linear feet)
Series 4: Financial Records, 1936-1965 (Box 5; 0.5 linear feet)
Series 5: Printed Materials, circa 1915-1987 (Boxes 5-6; 1.2 linear feet)
Series 6: Scrapbooks, 1912-1968(Boxes 6-7; 0.5 linear feet)
Series 7: Artwork, circa 1920-1945 (Box 6; 3 folders)
Series 8: Photographs, circa 1912-1961 (Boxes 6 and 8; 7 folders)
Existence and Location of Copies
Materials lent for microfilming are available on 35mm microfilm reels 287 and 2938-2939 at the Archives of American Art and through interlibrary loan.
Manuscripts; Painting -- Technique; Painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Printmakers -- New York (State) -- New York; Sketches; Graphic arts -- New York (State) -- New York; Etchings; Scrapbooks; Photographs; Poems; Castellón, Federico, 1914-1971; Christ-Janer, Albert, 1910-1973; Atelier Desjobert; Bohrod, Aaron; Dehn, Virginia E. (Virginia Engleman), 1922-2005; Eastman, Max, 1883-1969; Dehn, Mura; American Artists Group; Associated American Artists; Robinson, Boardman, 1876-1952; Spruance, Benton, 1904-1967; Thayer, Scofield, b. 1889; University of Missouri Press; Zigrosser, Carl, 1891-; Marsh, Reginald, 1898-1954; Lake, Eileen Hall; Olds, Elizabeth, 1896-1991; Mitchell, Olivia Dehn; Rattner, Abraham; Smith, William Arthur, 1918-1989; Shane, Fred, 1906-; Gag, Wanda, 1893-1946; Freeman, Joseph; Grosz, George, 1893-1959; Goetsch, Gustav F. (Gustav Frederick), 1877-1969; Kennedy Galleries; Hayter, Stanley William, 1901-1988; Kuh, Frederick, 1895-1978; Kertész, André
- Biographical Material, circa 1920-1968; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; (Box 1; 10 folders)
  Scope and Contents note
  This series includes address books, a biographical sketch, insurance policies, interview transcript, exhibition price lists, and leases. A folder of travel documents consists of correspondence, a set of fingerprints, and official government documents, obtained for a trip to Venezuela on assignment from Standard Oil to create art documenting the oil industry and contribution to the war efforts. Additionally there is a folder labeled government documents that contains a registration card and two affidavits signed by Dehn; one in connection with his 1926 marriage to Mura Dehn (neé Tsiperovich) and the other is in support of a U.S. non-immigrant visa for Willis Bock. Notably, exhibition price lists includes a list of lithographs that Dehn made with the master printer Desjobert in Paris, between July 1 and October 23, 1961.
  Arrangement note
  Folders in this series are arranged in alphabetical order by folder title.
  - Address Books, circa 1920-1968; Archival Resource Key; (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Biographical Sketch for Who's Who in Art, 1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Interview Transcript - Adolf Dehn and K. Osis, 1963, March 21; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Exhibition Price Lists, 1942-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Government Documents, 1926-1942; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Insurance Policies, 1939-1942; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Leases and Cornwall Town Deed, 1940-1944, circa 1968-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Medical Certificates, 1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Travel Documents - Venezuela and Paris, 1944-1945, circa 1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, circa 1919-1982; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; (Boxes 1-4; 3.5 linear feet)
  Series is comprised of Adolf Dehn's personal and professional correspondence, consisting of letters, postcards, greeting cards, and telegrams from family, close friends, artists, dealers, collectors and museum directors. Additionally there is a separate group of Virginia Dehn's correspondence. More detailed description is provided at the subseries level.
  The Correspondence series is arranged into 3 subseries:
  2.1: General and Personal Correspondence, circa 1919-1982
  2.2: Business Correspondence, circa 1923-1982
  2.3: Virginia Dehn Correspondence, 1966-1979
  - General and Personal Correspondence, circa 1919-1982; 2.1; Archival Resource Key
    Files consist of letters and cards that document his relationships with family, friends, artists and associates and to a lesser extent his work processes and travels. Letters written by Adolf Dehn are also included in this subseries, both in separate folders that primarily contain letters to his first wife Mura, and scattered throughout the subseries in the form of drafted responses to other correspondents.
    Notable correspondents include fellow artists George Biddle, Aaron Bohrod, Albert Christ-Janer, Wanda Gág, Reginald Marsh, Abraham Rattner, Boardman Robinson and Frederick Shane; associates from political and literary magazines including Max Eastman, Joseph Freeman, Frederick Kuh, and Scofield Thayer; and former gallery director and print curator Carl Zigrosser. The letters of artist Federico Castellon may be of particular interest as they contain numerous mentions of printmaking processes and descriptions of working with Parisian master printers Desjobert and Dimitri, with whom Dehn also worked.
    General and personal correspondence is arranged in alphabetical order by last name of the correspondent when it is known, and first name when it is not; there is also a file of unidentified correspondents. As a general rule, when extant, envelopes precede cards and letters and enclosures follow. Envelopes, which had at some earlier point been separated from correspondence, and get well cards are arranged in files at the end of the series.
    - Alexander, Sidney and Frances, circa 1951-1972; Archival Resource Key; (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 11-14)
    - A, 1941-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
      A., Ethel
      Adler, Elmer
      Adlerblum, Clara
      Alpine Lodge Resort
      American Consular Service
      Arms, John Taylor
      Audubon Artists, Inc.
      Auerbach-Levy
    - Bock, Valeska, 1927-1947; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Bock, Willis, circa 1930-1932, 1952; Archival Resource Key; (5 folders) (Box 1, Folder 17-21)
    - Bohrod, Aaron, 1945-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Braun, Phyllis and Sidney, circa 1959-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Breitman, Bebik, 1951-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Bridgman, Mrs. Luther ("Boots"), 1963-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Butler, Joseph and Dorothy, circa 1963-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - B, circa 1929-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27)
      Baker, Mildred
      Barber, John
      Barber, Joseph
      Bassett, Lawrence
      Bean, Marshall
      Beecher, Catharine
      Bendiner, Alfred
      Benney, Robert
      Berenda, Dr. Ruth
      Berly, Rosario
      Bernstein, Lumarie
      Biddle, George
      Biddle, Michael ?
      Blanch, Arnold
      Boni, charles
      Booth, Cameron
      Bowser, Frank
      Brenner, Dan
      Brown, Gladys
      Bui[ck], Jacob
    - Castellon, Federico and Hilda, 1961-1974; Archival Resource Key; (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 28-31)
    - Christ-Janer, Albert, 1940-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Church, John and Noreen, circa 1961-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - C, 1935-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 34)
      California State Library
      Calow, Richard
      Canadé, Eugene
      Chadeayne, Bob
      Chambers, George
      Chappell, Warren
      Christ-Janer, Marylon and Ed
      Clapp, Eleanor
      Clements, Frank Milton
      Clohset, Virginia
      Cochran, Daisy Dehn
      Cole, Sylvan
      Condé Nast
      Crafts, James
      Crowell, Robert
      Crowninshield, Frank
      Curry, William Lee
    - Dehn, Adolf (to Mura Dehn), circa 1928-1930; Archival Resource Key; (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 35-38)
    - Dehn, Adolf, circa 1922-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Dehn, Arthur and Emilie, 1922-1946, 1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Dehn Family, 1940 and undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Dehn, Mura, circa 1924-1939, 1969; Archival Resource Key; (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 42-44)
    - D, circa 1920-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 45)
      Davidson, Mr. and Mrs. Arthur O.
      De[l], Maggie
      DeKnight, [Avel?]
      DePeri, Jean
      Desjobert, Nicole and Philippe
      Diamond, Lillian
      Diamond, Sigmund and Shirley
      Dorne, Albert
      Dorne, Edna
    - Eggers, Alleyene, circa 1933-1935; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - E, circa 1924-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 47)
      Eastman, Max
      Eberman, Edwin
      Egilsrud, Johan S.
      Eichenberg, Fritz
      Elser, Helen
      Elwell, Lulu (Mrs. Hector H.)
      Er[?], A.
      Eulau, Henrietta
    - Freeman, Joseph, 1925-1927; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - F, 1941-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 49)
      Fitzpatrick, D.R.
      Florsheim, Richard
      Forni, Florence
      Foster, Betty
      Frickel, Genevieve
      Fuller, Mary (Mrs. B. Frank)
    - Gág, Wanda, 1919-1927; Archival Resource Key; (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 50-51)
    - Gág, Wanda, 1919-1927; Archival Resource Key; (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
    - Gundlach, Robert and Maggie, 1961-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - G, circa 1921-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Gahn, Joseph A.
      Garfield, George
      Getlein, Frank
      Geyer, Linda
      Gibson, Lydia
      Gille, Marjorie
      Godfrey
      Goebel, Dorothy
      Goetsch, Gustav
      Golden, Allen
      Goldstein, Ben
      González, Xavier
      Goodridge, Elinor
      Greathouse, W.S.
      Greenstein, Ben
      Greenwood, Marion
      Griffel, Maurice
      Grosz, George
      Guitar, Mary Anne
    - Hempel, Mayra, 1936-1937; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Heyman, Marcus, 1941, circa 1963-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Howland, Gareth, 1919-1925; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Humans, Maria, 1945; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - H-J, 1922-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
      Hagerman, Percy
      Hale, Robert B.
      Hamaguchi, Yozo
      Harbeson, John
      Harrison, B[ob?]
      Haskell, Helen (Mrs. Douglas)
      Hechenbleikner, Louis
      Hein
      Helck, Peter
      Hempel, Willy
      Hendricks, Harry
      Hennefrund, Elizabeth
      Hodgins, Eric and Eleanor
      Hoessein, M
      Horner, Peter
      Howell, A[?] (Mrs. Peter)
      Humphreys, Earle
      Huntley, Victoria
      Inokuma, Genichiro
      Jacobs, M.E.
      Jensen, Karen Marie
      Jolink, Bette
    - Kuh, Frederick and Renata, 1919-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - K, 1940-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
      K., Homer[?]
      Keady, Joe (G.J.)
      Kent, Sally
      Klau, Judy
      Klein, Samuel
      Klemm, Robert (Mrs. Douglas)
      Knight, Eric
      Knight, Jere
      Kretzmann, Adalbert Raphael
      Kruse, Vera
      Kumar, Ravi
    - Lake, Eileen Hall, circa 1933-1943; Archival Resource Key; (7 folders) (Box 2, Folder 13-19)
    - Larrabee, Harold, 1919-1927, 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Lee, Etta, 1932; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Lull, Jeri (Mrs. E. E.), 1968-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - L, circa 1920-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 23)
      L[?], Jo Ouren
      La Steed, G[?]
      Lall, Kiran ("Tookie")
      Lamping, Mrs. Bernard
      Landau, Fran
      Lauritz, Paul
      Lebeau, Frank (Mrs. Douglas)
      Lee, Doris
      Lewis, Sinclair
      Lie, Jonas
      Lichtenstein, Samuel
      Litchfield, Donald
      Logue, Alberta
      Lotos Club
      Luid, Helen
    - McBride, Irene, 1937; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Mitchell, Olivia Dehn, 1922 and undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - M, 1926-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 26)
      MacGregor, Robert
      Mack, Caroline
      Magill, Wallace
      Malkin, Jean
      Malkine, Yvette Ledoux
      Mandel, Estelle
      Manuelito, Dennis
      Marbury, Elizabeth
      Marks, Gerald
      Marsh, Felicia
      Marsh, Reginald
      Märtens, Klaus
      Mayers, Ralph and Bena
      Maxwell, Donald
      McBride, Henry
      McCue, Lillian
      McGee, Olivia
      McGeeney, Joe
      McIntyre, Jen and Bob[?]
      McPhill, Peter
      Milch, Harold and Harriet
      Miller, Charles
      Moe, Vesta (Mrs. Lester)
      Monahan, Gene
      Moore, Douglas
      Moore, Ruth
      Moyer, Verna
      Muench, Jack
      Muir, Willa
      Mulloy, John
    - N-O, circa 1941-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 27)
      Nash, William
      Navas, Elizabeth
      Nuessle, Amelia
      Nuessle, William "Bill"
      Oldfield, E.
      Olds, Elizabeth
      Olesen, Anna Dickie
      Orloff, Arthur
    - Orcutt, Lillian, 1919-1968; Archival Resource Key; (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 28-29)
    - Pracht, Gretchen, 1954-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - P, 1941-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 31)
      Pearson, John
      Peters, Carol
      Pfister, Ed
      Pierce, Bruce
      Plyer, Freddy
      Polk, R. Brooke
      Pritchard, Beth
      Pollack, Raphael
      Pollak, D.
    - Rattner, Abraham and Esther, circa 1965-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Robinson, Boardman "Mike", 1920-1946; Archival Resource Key; (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 33-34)
    - R, circa 1919-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 35)
      R[?bert], Janice
      Reinhardt, Ed
      Riccius, Hermann
      Richardson, Rebecca
      Roesler, Nora (Mrs. C.G.)
      Rose, Dorothy
      Rosenhauft, Hans
      Rosenev, Simon
      Ruotolo, Onorio
      Ryan, Marion
    - Schreiber, Georges, 1944, 1961-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 36)